Here we'll look at risk versus
uncertainty. These terms aren't
interchangeable - they're fundamentally
different. The left shows a probability
distribution - that's risk. The right
shows a black swan - that's uncertainty.
John Maynard Keynes, one of the most
influential economists of the 20th
century, had important insights about
uncertainty.
Keynes said: "By uncertain knowledge, I do
not mean merely to distinguish what is
known for certain from what is only
probable." Uncertainty isn't just
improbable - it's fundamentally
unknowable.
Keynes continues: "The sense in which I
use the term is that in which the prospect
of a European war is uncertain, or the
price of copper and the rate of interest
twenty years hence are uncertain."
Warren Buffett adds: "Risk comes from not
knowing what you are doing." Risk stems
from ignorance or lack of understanding.
These two perspectives define our
framework.
Left side: Risk means known probability.
Right side: Uncertainty means unknown
probability. Rolling a standard six-sided
die demonstrates risk. Each outcome has
one-in-six probability. We can measure it
and assign probabilities.
Corporate bonds illustrate risk. Credit
ratings, historical default rates, and
financial statements provide data. We
estimate default probabilities and model
scenarios. Data makes it risk, not
uncertainty.
Car insurance premiums demonstrate
measurable risk. Actuarial tables allow
insurance companies to assign
probabilities to different accident types
using driver age, past accidents,
location, and vehicle type. Your insurer
analyzes your profile against millions of
data points. They calculate precise
probabilities for your demographic. Known
probabilities mean measurable risk.
Now uncertainty. Technological disruption
is the first example. Could anyone in 1995
predict smartphones would revolutionize
banking? Could you assign probabilities?
No - you couldn't imagine it coming.
COVID-19 demonstrates uncertainty
perfectly. Early 2020, no one could model
global lockdown probabilities or economic
impacts. This was unprecedented. Without
historical data, we can't assign
meaningful probabilities. That's the core
difference from risk.
Regime changes in stable countries
represent uncertainty. A country stable
for decades - can you calculate regime
change probability? No. These are unique,
one-off events without probability
distributions.
Nassim Nicholas Taleb defined Black Swan
events. A Black Swan has three attributes:
First, it's an outlier - outside regular
expectations. Second, it carries extreme
impact. Third, despite being an outlier,
humans create explanations afterward,
making it seem explainable and
predictable. After events happen, we
convince ourselves we could've predicted
them. But we couldn't. That's uncertainty.
So risk is measurable - we assign
probabilities, model it, hedge with
derivatives. Uncertainty involves unknown
unknowns - we can't assign probabilities
and need different strategies. This
distinction is fundamental.